University Council; Records ua100
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
University Council Records
1844 - 2018 January 17
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
State University of New York at Albany--University Council
ua100
17 cubic ft.
39 captures
139 Digital Files
Includes meeting minutes and supporting documentation of the Executive Committee of the New York State Normal School, 1844-1990; the Board of Trustees 1890-1928; and Board of Visitors, 1928-1939, of the New York State College for Teachers; and minutes, correspondence, reports, and publications of the University Council, 1965-2015. The power of the original Executive Committee, Board of Trustees, Board of Visitors extended to the hiring and firing of all employees, prescribing the curriculum including the texts used in courses. These bodies reported jointly to the Board of Regents of the University of the State of New York and the Superintendent of Education, the later individual serving as Chairman of successive bodies. The powers of the University Council, created by the SUNY Board of Trustees in 1954, are far more restricted, being limited to nominating presidents, naming buildings, and reviewing and approving major policy changes and initiatives.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Web Archives
Access
Access to public records and material created longer than 20 years ago is unrestricted.
Records of presidential search committees are closed for 20 years due to the presence of personally identifiable information.
Records are closed or restricted by file series, please contact an archivist to view individual material that may no longer be closed.
Red asterisks (***) denote closed or restricted items.
Acquisition Information
All items in this manuscript group were transferred to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives by the Office of the President and the Secretary to the University Council.
Administrative History
The University Council is the successor to the Executive Committee of the State Normal School at Albany created by "An Act for the establishment of a Normal School" passed by the State Legislature on May 7, 1844. The Executive Committee so established consisted of five members, one of whom was to be the Superintendent of the Common Schools, later the Superintendent of Education. The Committee reported to the Superintendent of Education and the Regents of the University of the State of New York. The presence of the Superintendent of the Common Schools (and his successors, the Superintendents and Commissioners of Education) on the principal governing body of the Normal School--State College for Teachers between 1844 and 1937 undoubtedly meant that the Albany Board was in a strong position to influence school policy. The Executive Committee and its successors have always included prominent local professionals, business leaders, and politicians with an interest in education.
The Executive Committee was responsible for the "care, management and government of the school," were bound to make "full and detailed reports" to the superintendent and Regents, and were to "recommend the rules and regulations which they deemed necessary and proper for said school." The Executive Committee exercised wide powers at the Normal School, extending from the supervision of hiring and dismissing faculty and staff to the choice of texts and the methods of teaching. In 1909 the title of the Executive Committee was changed to Board of Trustees, but the composition and powers of the newly named Board remained the same.
A 1928 reorganization of education in New York resulted in the replacement of the Board of Trustees by a Board of Visitors in 1929. This new Board consisted of seven persons (an increase of two) appointed by the Board of Regents upon the recommendation of the Commissioner of Education. The Board of Visitors continued to have the right to nominate presidents, "visit and inspect" the school, and was mandated to meet at least three times a year. The Board's powers to "visit and inspect" specifically included the power to "keep themselves informed as to the teaching force, activities and other need of such schools." The Board was also required to make periodic reports to the Regents. The Rules of the Board of Regents specifically directed boards to pay special attention to the "teaching force, activities and other needs of such colleges" and "to the physical condition of the school plant--repairs, replacements, new buildings, equipment...."
Despite the continuity of powers between the original Executive Committee and the Board of Visitors it is apparent that during the twentieth century, due to the increased size and complexity of the College, the active administrative role of the Board had diminished. During the Brubacher presidency, 1915-1939, the minutes of the Board were dominated by the President's reports and program proposals. Under President Sayles, 1940-48, the minutes of only two board meeting exist. Perhaps in response to this development the NYSCT Board was instructed by the Regents in 1944, along with other Boards, to take an "active interest in the affairs of the Teachers College and to report annually upon the activities of the Board, including such recommendations as the Board wishes to bring to the attention of the Board of Regents." No evidence exists as to whether this charge was actually carried out.
With the creation of the State University of New York in 1948 and university-wide Board of Trustees the oversight functions and indeed the continued functioning of the Board of Visitors became less clear. The omnibus State University Education Bill effective September 1, 1953, called for the continued existence of current Boards of Visitors. While no minutes have been found to for the Board of Visitors or its successor, the College Council, between 1945 and 1960, we do have evidence that the Board of Visitors continued to function in some capacity until at least 1952,''.
The Board of Visitors appears to have been replaced by the College Council in 1954. According to Section 356 of the Education Law, Chapter 525, the function of the College Council was to "supervise locally" subject to the "general management, supervision and control and in accordance with rules established by the state university trustees, the operations and affairs of each state-operated institution of the State University...." No longer were the Regents and the Commissioner of Education were the direct overseers of the State College for Teachers. The Commissioner of Education did not have a seat on the Council. The College Council was to consist of nine members appointed by the Governor and was presided over by a chairman, also appointed by the Governor. The specific powers reserved to the College Council were to nominate candidates for President; to review all major plans of the President and to make recommendations respecting those plans to the Board of Trustees of SUNY; to make regulations regarding the maintenance of buildings, grounds and equipment, to review budget requests; foster advisory citizen's committees; name buildings and grounds "make regulations governing the conduct and behavior of students"; "prescribe for an. exercise supervision over student housing and safety"; make annual and special reports to the trustees as needed; perform other duties as assigned by the trustees; and "make and establish, and from time to time alter and amend, such regulations pertaining to the affairs of its institution, not inconsistent with law or the rules of the state university trustees may be necessary or appropriate to carry out effectively the foregoing powers and duties."
The College Council was renamed the University Council in 1963. The functions, powers, and reporting responsibility remain unchanged with the current Council. In 1975, the Council was enlarged by the addition of one non-voting student member as the result of the passage of Chapter 587 of the New York State Education Law, 1975.
Scope and Contents
Includes meeting minutes and supporting documentation of the Executive Committee of the New York State Normal School, 1844-90; the Board of Trustees 1890-1928; and Board of Visitors, 1928-39, of the New York State College for Teachers; and minutes, correspondence, reports, and publications of the University Council, 1965-85. The power of the original Executive Committee, Board of Trustees, Board of Visitors extended to the hiring and firing of all employees, prescribing the curriculum including the texts used in courses. These bodies reported jointly to the Board of Regents of the University of the State of New York and the Superintendent of Education, the later individual serving as Chairman of successive bodies. The powers of the University Council, created by the SUNY Board of Trustees in 1954, are far more restricted, being limited to nominating presidents, naming buildings, and reviewing and approving major policy changes and initiatives.
The records contain the minutes of the Executive Committee (1844-1909), Board of Trustees (1909-28), the Board of Visitors (1928-39, 1944-45), and the University Council, 1965-89. The records illustrate the changes in the role of this body. They also provide an oversight of the issues affecting the University and its predecessor bodies during these years. During the nineteenth and the early twentieth century the Executive Committee was very involved in the day-to-day affairs of the State Normal School, the State Normal College, and the New York State College for Teachers. It was responsible for the hiring of teachers, the curriculum, the selection of text books, school regulations, the conditions of the school buildings, and the preparation of the budget. These issues are prominent throughout the minutes. Other issues considered by the Executive Committee include: negotiation with Albany City Council concerning the provision of a building for the State Normal School, 1844; the establishment of an Experimental School, the practice teaching school which eventually became the Milne School, 1845; funding for the education of Native American youth, 1849; the acquisition of new grounds at Willett Street and Madison Avenue, 1883; the planning and building of the present downtown campus, 1906-07; the establishment of a four year rather than a two year curriculum, 1908. Prominent issues considered by the Board of Trustees included the impact on the German department of the decline of German majors, 1919; the inadequate number of student living facilities, and the submission of plans to rectify this situation, 1920-26. The Board of Visitors formulated a response to the National Defense Council of Albany's condemnation of students who were unwilling to bear arms in the event of a war in Europe, 1933; and established an the Emergency College to help high school graduates who would otherwise have been unable to finance their education plans during the Great Depression in 1933.
The role of the current University Council is quite different from that of its predecessor bodies. It now acts primarily as an advisory body to the University. It plays a significant role in shaping relations between the University and the State Legislature, and it also acts as a bridge between the University and the community. The minutes of the late 1960s through the 1980s illustrate the Council's role in each of these areas. Ongoing concerns throughout this period include institutional policy development and implementation, the establishment of University regulations, academic programs, hiring and admissions, the University budget, honoring professional staff and members of the community committed to the development of the University, naming ground and buildings. Other more specific concerns during this period include: discussions of the possible establishment of University Law and Medical Schools, 1967; the need for a clear statement from the Council concerning student dissent and freedom of speech, 1967; the Board of Trustees resolution ordering all SUNY institutions to submit regulations concerning student conduct with the Secretary of State, 1968; the need for a narcotics education program on campus, 1968; the establishment of the Department of Afro-American Studies, 1969; student unrest on campus, 1971; Affirmative Action, 1972; the Chancellor's request that the University assume responsibility for an Education Opportunity Center in Albany, 1973; the decision of the Commissioner of Education to deregister the Ph.D. programs in English and History, 1975-76; the University's Task Force on Priorities and Resources, 1976; the termination of seven Doctoral, five Masters and eight Bachelors programs, 1976; the need for more off-campus housing, 1978; drug and alcohol abuse, 1980; the Student Assembly's structure and concerns, 1981; the establishment of awards to members of the community for their service to the university, 1983; the need to strengthen and expand the relationship between campus research activities and the private sector through the formation of a Center for Research and Development, 1984; the expansion of computing facilities, 1985; student health issues, in particular AIDS, 1987; minority issues, programs, and enrollment, 1987.
Arrangement of the Collection
This collection has no series.
College administrators; Administrative records; Minutes (administrative records); Digital Audio Formats; Web Archives; Digital Files; Wages -- New York (State); State University of New York at Albany
- Website of the University Council, 2007 October 31 - 2018 January 17; 1; 39 captures
  URL
  http://www.albany.edu/council/
  Access Requirements
  The item contains web archives preserved as WARC files. They must be access though web archival replay tools such as the "Wayback Machine." The links here direct you to files hosted by the Internet Archive, but you may also request WARC files.
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Web crawling is managed through the Internet Archive's Archive-It service.
  This item is not a seed within an Archive-it collection, but capures of this page are found within:
  collection: University at Albany, SUNY Website
  created_date: 2012-09-17T13:15:00Z
  created_by: bkeough
  state: ACTIVE
  last_updated_date: 2016-09-26T23:38:05Z
  last_updated_by: system
  Web Collection
  - University at Albany - University Council, 2007 October 31
    This crawl was performed by the Internet Archive, not the UAlbany web archiving program, so the provenance is unknown.
  - University at Albany - University Council, 2008 January 1
  - University at Albany - University Council, 2008 September 14
  - University at Albany - University Council Members, 2009 January 25
  - University at Albany - University Council Members, 2010 March 22
  - University at Albany - University Council Members, 2010 May 23
  - University at Albany - University Council Members, 2010 July 26
  - University at Albany - University Council Members, 2010 July 26
  - University Council - Home - University at Albany - SUNY, 2011 October 8
  - University Council - Home - University at Albany - SUNY, 2012 February 18
  - University Council - Home - University at Albany - SUNY, 2012 July 1
  - University Council - Home - University at Albany - SUNY, 2012 September 30
  - University Council - Home - University at Albany - SUNY, 2012 December 1
  - University Council - Home - University at Albany - SUNY, 2013 February 1
  - University Council - Home - University at Albany - SUNY, 2013 February 17
  - University Council - Home - University at Albany - SUNY, 2013 May 1
  - University Council - Home - University at Albany - SUNY, 2013 May 8
    This item had no crawl rules.
    The CDX index for this capture did not contain crawl information.
  - WARC file for University Council - Home - University at Albany - SUNY, 2013 May 8
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
    Researchers interested in data analysis with web archives may request a WARC file. WARC files are very large and difficult to work with. Your request may take time to process, and we may be unable to deliver your request remotely. Please consult an archivist if you are interested in advanced research with web archives.
  - University Council - Home - University at Albany - SUNY, 2013 September 11
  - WARC file for University Council - Home - University at Albany - SUNY, 2013 September 11
  - University Council - Home - University at Albany - SUNY, 2013 October 1
  - University Council - Home - University at Albany - SUNY, 2013 October 30
  - WARC file for University Council - Home - University at Albany - SUNY, 2013 October 30
  - University Council - Home - University at Albany - SUNY, 2014 October 1
  - WARC file for University Council - Home - University at Albany - SUNY, 2014 October 1
  - University Council - Home - University at Albany - SUNY, 2015 September 17
    crawl: 173356
    Crawl Times
    start_date: 2015-09-17T16:57:20Z
    original_start_date: 2015-09-17T16:57:20Z
    last_resumption: None
    processing_end_date: 2015-09-23T01:24:03Z
    end_date: 2015-09-23T00:16:53Z
    elapsed_ms: 458363239
    Crawl Types
    type: MONTHLY
    recurrence_type: MONTHLY
    pdfs_only: False
    test: False
    Crawl Limits
    time_limit: 432000
    document_limit: None
    byte_limit: None
    crawl_stop_requested: None
    Crawl Results
    status: FINISHED_TIME_LIMIT
    discovered_count: 367719
    novel_count: 26001
    duplicate_count: 206766
    resumption_count: 0
    queued_count: 134952
    downloaded_count: 232767
    download_failures: 237
    warc_revisit_count: 206761
    warc_url_count: 232678
    total_data_in_kbs: 101606587
    duplicate_bytes: 94029637527
    warc_compressed_bytes: 157865634
    Crawl Technical Details
    doc_rate: 0.51
    kb_rate: 221.0
  - WARC file for University Council - Home - University at Albany - SUNY, 2015 September 17
  - University Council - Home - University at Albany - SUNY, 2015 December 17
    crawl: 187970
    start_date: 2015-12-17T16:55:04Z
    original_start_date: 2015-12-17T16:55:04Z
    processing_end_date: 2015-12-22T21:57:26Z
    end_date: 2015-12-22T21:40:44Z
    elapsed_ms: 449129872
    discovered_count: 304232
    novel_count: 13877
    duplicate_count: 191764
    queued_count: 98591
    downloaded_count: 205641
    download_failures: 234
    warc_revisit_count: 191759
    warc_url_count: 205547
    total_data_in_kbs: 60257781
    duplicate_bytes: 60588343215
    warc_compressed_bytes: 34726906
    doc_rate: 0.46
    kb_rate: 134.0
  - WARC file for University Council - Home - University at Albany - SUNY, 2015 December 17
  - University Council - Home - University at Albany - SUNY, 2016 March 17
    crawl: 201840
    Crawl Rules
    Ignore Robots.txt for www.albany.edu (last updated 2016-02-11)
    Ignore Robots.txt for www.alumni.albany.edu (last updated 2016-02-11)
    Ignore Robots.txt for www.ualbanysports.com (last updated 2016-02-11)
    Ignore Robots.txt for library.albany.edu (last updated 2017-05-19)
    Ignore Robots.txt for alumni.albany.edu (last updated 2016-02-11)
    Ignore Robots.txt for asrc.albany.edu (last updated 2016-02-11)
    Ignore Robots.txt for atmos.albany.edu (last updated 2016-02-11)
    Ignore Robots.txt for bioinformatics.albany.edu (last updated 2016-02-11)
    Ignore Robots.txt for cela.albany.edu (last updated 2016-02-11)
    Ignore Robots.txt for choose.albany.edu (last updated 2016-02-11)
    Ignore Robots.txt for cs.albany.edu (last updated 2016-02-11)
    Ignore Robots.txt for csda.albany.edu (last updated 2016-02-11)
    Ignore Robots.txt for imls.ctg.albany.edu (last updated 2016-02-11)
    Ignore Robots.txt for www.ctg.albany.edu (last updated 2017-05-19)
    Ignore Robots.txt for cwig.albany.edu (last updated 2016-02-11)
    Ignore Robots.txt for events.albany.edu (last updated 2016-02-11)
    Ignore Robots.txt for hr.albany.edu (last updated 2016-02-11)
    Ignore Robots.txt for ibl.albany.edu (last updated 2016-02-11)
    Ignore Robots.txt for illiad.albany.edu (last updated 2016-02-11)
    Ignore Robots.txt for liblogs.albany.edu (last updated 2017-05-19)
    Ignore Robots.txt for libguides.library.albany.edu (last updated 2016-02-11)
    Ignore Robots.txt for scholarsarchive.library.albany.edu (last updated 2016-02-11)
    Ignore Robots.txt for listserv.albany.edu (last updated 2016-02-11)
    Ignore Robots.txt for m.albany.edu (last updated 2016-02-11)
    Ignore Robots.txt for math.albany.edu (last updated 2016-02-11)
    Ignore Robots.txt for omega.math.albany.edu (last updated 2016-02-11)
    Ignore Robots.txt for mumford.albany.edu (last updated 2016-02-11)
    Ignore Robots.txt for nyjm.albany.edu (last updated 2016-02-11)
    Ignore Robots.txt for pdp.albany.edu (last updated 2016-02-11)
    Ignore Robots.txt for resnet.albany.edu (last updated 2016-02-11)
    Ignore Robots.txt for rit.albany.edu (last updated 2016-02-11)
    Ignore Robots.txt for cyberphysics.rit.albany.edu (last updated 2016-02-11)
    Ignore Robots.txt for rna.albany.edu (last updated 2016-02-11)
    Ignore Robots.txt for slsc.albany.edu (last updated 2017-05-19)
    Ignore Robots.txt for uaems.albany.edu (last updated 2016-02-11)
    Ignore Robots.txt for uapps.albany.edu (last updated 2016-02-11)
    Ignore Robots.txt for wiki.albany.edu (last updated 2016-02-11)
    start_date: 2016-03-17T16:54:59Z
    original_start_date: 2016-03-17T16:54:59Z
    processing_end_date: 2016-03-22T18:02:10Z
    end_date: 2016-03-22T16:56:57Z
    elapsed_ms: 432107388
    discovered_count: 639552
    novel_count: 138564
    duplicate_count: 332568
    queued_count: 168420
    downloaded_count: 471132
    download_failures: 1411433
    warc_revisit_count: 332563
    warc_url_count: 471037
    total_data_in_kbs: 116820623
    duplicate_bytes: 113225737713
    warc_compressed_bytes: 765920585
    doc_rate: 1.09
    kb_rate: 270.0
  - WARC file for University Council - Home - University at Albany - SUNY, 2016 March 17
  - University Council - Home - University at Albany - SUNY, 2016 September 17
    crawl: 236726
    Block host dev.library.albany.edu
    start_date: 2016-09-17T16:55:32Z
    original_start_date: 2016-09-17T16:55:32Z
    processing_end_date: 2016-09-22T19:45:41Z
    end_date: 2016-09-22T17:03:18Z
    elapsed_ms: 432208662
    discovered_count: 1414002
    novel_count: 188377
    duplicate_count: 898376
    queued_count: 327249
    downloaded_count: 1086753
    download_failures: 287
    warc_revisit_count: 898345
    warc_url_count: 1086634
    total_data_in_kbs: 205611728
    duplicate_bytes: 200652210118
    warc_compressed_bytes: 309191153
    doc_rate: 2.51
    kb_rate: 475.0
  - WARC file for University Council - Home - University at Albany - SUNY, 2016 September 17
  - University Council - Home - University at Albany - SUNY, 2017 May 17
    crawl: 301465
    Host Rule Type C CONTAINS meg.library.albany.edu:8080/archive/search? (last updated 2017-05-11)
    start_date: 2017-05-17T16:55:17Z
    original_start_date: 2017-05-17T16:55:17Z
    processing_end_date: 2017-05-23T00:29:43Z
    end_date: 2017-05-22T21:46:25Z
    elapsed_ms: 449440076
    discovered_count: 2923335
    novel_count: 388249
    duplicate_count: 1238165
    queued_count: 1296921
    downloaded_count: 1626414
    download_failures: 336
    warc_revisit_count: 1238113
    warc_url_count: 1626286
    total_data_in_kbs: 265327774
    duplicate_bytes: 251274786133
    warc_compressed_bytes: 3306915146
    doc_rate: 3.62
    kb_rate: 590.0
  - WARC file for University Council - Home - University at Albany - SUNY, 2017 May 17
  - University Council - Home - University at Albany - SUNY, 2017 July 17
    crawl: 315280
    Applied scope rule: BLOCK_HOST for host dev.library.albany.edu (last updated (created 2016-08-09, last updated 2016-08-09)